when i was a student uh at columbia
当我还是哥伦比亚大学的学生时
one day i was accidentally brought
有一天我不小心被带到了
into a lecture
进入讲座
uh
呃
by somebody
由某人
whose name that sounds very strange to
他的名字听起来很奇怪
me it was the first couple years as i
这是我的头几年
arrived in america
抵达美国
english wasn't quite there
英语不太好
the name sounds like a free lunch buffet
这个名字听起来像是免费的自助午餐
but that lecture
但那场讲座
buff buffett really fundamentally uh
buff巴菲特真的从根本上呃
changed the correct true director of my
改变了我的正确导演
life in america and really give the
在美国的生活并真正给予
career that i enjoyed immensely today
我今天非常享受的职业
and so it gave me a great pleasure to be
所以这让我很高兴
back into this title of the setting to
返回到该设置的标题
communicate directly with the student
直接与学生沟通
and today i want to talk a little bit
今天我想谈谈
about some of the
关于一些
value investing
价值投资
the basic concept of values
价值观的基本概念
investing obviously is
投资显然是
many many decades old but today i think
几十年前的事了，但今天我想
it is as relevant
它是相关的
as
作为
when it was first laid out by benjamin
当本杰明第一次布置它时
graham
格雷厄姆
and columbia
和哥伦比亚
six seven decades ago
六七十年前
and essentially just the three basic
基本上只是三个基本的
ideas
想法
the first one is the stock is not a
第一个是股票不是
piece of paper that you treat but it
你对待的一张纸，但它
represents fractional ownership of a
代表某物的部分所有权
company
公司
and therefore evaluating the stock
因此评估股票
ought to really have a basic barriers
确实应该有一个基本的障碍
of evaluating the company as a whole
对公司进行整体评估
and then secondly that you value in any
其次，你重视任何
financial asset
金融资产
that
那个
you have to really predict in the future
你必须真正预测未来
the discounted cash flow of the future
未来的贴现现金流量
cash earnings
现金收入
and the future is inherently
未来本质上是
difficult
困难
to predict
预测
and
和
therefore you really want to leave
所以你真的想离开
yourself a margin of safety
给自己留出安全边际
so that you could be wrong
这样你就可能错了
or you could be right but because the
或者你可能是对的，但因为
future is a distribution of
未来是一个分布
opportunity i mean statistic
机会我的意思是统计数据
possibilities
可能性
say you bet on something that ninety
假设你打赌九十
percent of the chances you could be
你可能成为的可能性的百分比
right
对
but then the ten percent chance occurred
但百分之十的机会发生了
so
所以
all of a sudden become a hundred percent
一下子就变成百分百了
so you want to leave enough a margin of
所以你想留足够的余量
safety in other words you want to buy
安全，换句话说，你想买
the low enough of a price
价格足够低
even if all the adverse
即使一切不利
events occurred against you in the
发生了针对您的事件
future
未来
you will still be in the game it doesn't
你仍然会在游戏中，但事实并非如此
mean you won't lose money but it just
意味着你不会赔钱，但只是
means that you not lose so much that
意味着你不会失去那么多
you'll be out of the game because
你将会退出游戏，因为
investing is really a long game
投资确实是一场持久战
it complains over the life of anybody's
它抱怨任何人的生活
career
职业生涯
and so you want to be really in the game
所以你想真正参与到游戏中
somehow over the long haul
从长远来看
and the third concept is mr market
第三个概念是市场先生
to figure out a frame of mind to think
找出一个思考的心态
that
那个
when the market is against you
当市场对你不利时
you look at it as a
你把它看作是
a neurotic
神经质的
uh
呃
mr market that's prone for emotional and
市场先生容易情绪化
irrational behaviors
非理性行为
so those are the three basic concepts at
这就是三个基本概念
the heart of it is obviously it is this
其核心显然就是这个
bargain idea that you want to really get
你真正想要得到的讨价还价的想法
what you pay for
你付出什么
now
现在
obviously that's what everybody wanted
显然这就是每个人都想要的
and if everybody want the same thing you
如果每个人都想要同样的东西
would think that
会认为
all of the professional investors will
所有的专业投资者都会
be value investors
做价值投资者
and that's just the further
这只是进一步的
thing from truth
来自真理的事情
in fact value investing is properly
事实上价值投资是正确的
practiced constitutes a tiny small
练习构成了一个微小的小
minority of all the investment
占全部投资的少数
professionals
专业人士
majority of the people hold a different
大多数人持有不同的看法
views
意见
and let me just articulate for them the
让我向他们阐明
alternative view of providing investing
提供投资的另类观点
number one
第一名
yes stock
是的库存
legally represents fractional claims of
合法地代表部分索赔
fractional ownership
部分所有权
but is first and foremost a piece of a
但首先也是最重要的是
paper you can treat all the time
您可以随时处理的纸张
and therefore it follows that successful
因此，成功的结论是
investing lies in the successful
投资在于成功
guessing
猜测
of the stock movement
股票走势的
based on whatever informed theories or
基于任何有根据的理论或
practices
实践
that you can find
你可以找到
and thirdly
第三
that the market is to be respected
市场应该受到尊重
indeed to be feared
确实令人恐惧
because they really through the market
因为他们真正通过市场
you can actually find a value and
你实际上可以找到一个值并且
through the market you can actually buy
通过市场你实际上可以买到
and
和
sell
卖
so this scenario ago a different view
所以这个场景之前有不同的看法
and it sounds even more persuasive
听起来更有说服力
than the first reviews that i laid out
比我列出的第一个评论
as a value investor
作为价值投资者
in fact i would say majority of the
事实上我会说大多数
people when you follow the ladder rather
当你沿着梯子走时的人
than the formal
比正式的
so as a young student trying to get into
所以作为一个年轻的学生试图进入
the business which way do you follow
你走哪条路
i would suggest that before you do that
我建议你在这样做之前
you will go through some fundamental
你会经历一些基本的
studies as to the result
研究结果
of there is a different approach and
有一种不同的方法和
philosophies
哲学
unfortunately there has been numerous
不幸的是已经有很多
studies
研究
have done because
已经做了，因为
we kept a pretty good track record uh
我们保持了很好的记录呃
over the last 100 years that we used to
在过去的100年里我们曾经
visit
访问
and and all the studies that have
以及所有的研究
given a mistaken conclusion
给出了错误的结论
that the true value of investors as a
投资者作为投资者的真正价值
practiced
练习过的
have consistently uh
一直呃
outperformed the market whereas all just
跑赢市场，而一切都只是
about all other strategies
关于所有其他策略
either match the market or
要么与市场相匹配，要么
severely underperform the market over a
严重落后于市场
long period of time
很长一段时间
now you can dispute the result of it but
现在你可以对结果提出异议，但是
i think the evidence is pretty
我认为证据很充分
persuasive
有说服力的
and so the question becomes if that were
所以问题就变成了如果那是
the case
案件
of course the study also concluded that
当然研究还得出结论
the
的
true value investors that is a properly
真正的价值投资者是一个适当的
practiced really are a tiny small
练得确实是一点点
percentage
百分比
of investing
投资的
professionals that is also a very
专业人士，这也是一个非常
interesting study and but they really do
有趣的研究，但他们确实做到了
conform
符合
our day-to-day observation having been
我们的日常观察是
in this profession for close to 20 years
从事这个行业近20年
so why is the case why is the case
那么为什么会这样 为什么会这样
if the
如果
empirical studies conclude
实证研究得出结论
overwhelmingly
压倒性地
that going through the value investing
通过价值投资
is is the way to go
这是要走的路
and
和
the philosophies of the practice are
实践的哲学是
being well articulated for seven decades
七十年来一直清晰可见
and well practiced and
并经过良好实践和
publicized by
公布于
tremendous successful examples such as
巨大的成功例子，例如
mr buffett as we just mentioned
正如我们刚才提到的巴菲特先生
why not more people follow what they do
为什么没有更多的人跟随他们所做的事情
what it turn out has a lot to do with
结果有很大关系
human psychology
人类心理学
in manual investing
在手动投资中
you have to have this
你必须有这个
frame of mind that
的心态
if you did your work correctly or the
如果你的工作做得正确或者
market against you
市场对你不利
you should be comfortable standing alone
你独自站立应该很舒服
and this is the concept behind mr market
这就是市场先生背后的概念
but that's really very difficult to do
但这真的很难做到
it is a very
这是一个非常
unnatural thing to do
不自然的事情
when the whole market is against you
当整个市场都对你不利时
when everybody else you really think
当其他人你真的认为
you're stupid
你很蠢
and uh erotic and wrong
呃，色情而且错误
and you now tend to think everybody else
而你现在倾向于认为其他人
isn't mr marketing rational neurotic
营销先生不是理性神经质吗
uh that is very very unnatural things to
呃，这是非常非常不自然的事情
do and was
做和曾经
the borderlines of the self delusion
自我欺骗的界限
indeed that's probably most people's
确实这可能是大多数人的
view about you at the time
当时对你的看法
you look quite ridiculous and very
你看起来很可笑而且很
uncomfortable
不舒服
in fact our very
事实上我们非常
evolution requires a certain deal of
进化需要一定的过程
conformity
顺应性
think about over the millennials over
想想千禧一代
the uh millions of years of evolutionary
呃数百万年的进化
past
过去
our ancestors our animal predecessors uh
我们的祖先 我们的动物祖先 呃
you know basically hunting groups
你基本上知道狩猎团体
and if one was left out and disagree
如果有人被排除在外并且不同意
with everybody else in the group
与小组中的其他人
very easily that one is not the one to
很容易那个人就不是那个人
survive
生存
so all the genes that have survived in
所以所有幸存下来的基因
the past are the ones content to
过去的人满足于
extreme degree of conformity
极端的一致性
and conformity
和整合
also works very well as
也很好用
for human society because we are
对于人类社会来说，因为我们是
at the end at the heart of social
最后在社会的核心
animals
动物
we need in that
我们需要在那
sense of glue of a conformity and the
一致性和粘合感
sympathy
同情
compassion to bring the society in peace
慈悲为怀，社会安宁
and live together
并住在一起
so you need a certain mutated genes in a
所以你需要某种突变基因
sense to be utterly comfortable to stand
站立时感觉完全舒适
alone when everybody else disagree with
当其他人不同意时独自一人
you
你
now that is the reason at least that's
现在这就是原因，至少是这样
one of the reasons the financial market
金融市场不景气的原因之一
in itself is not that efficient
本身效率并不高
free market ever since it was practiced
自由市场自实行以来
a lot in time about two three hundred
很多时间大约两三百
years ago
几年前
has worked remarkably well
效果非常好
but it's worked most
但它最有效
remarkably well primarily i think
我主要认为非常好
goods and services
商品和服务
physical goods and definable services
实物商品和可定义的服务
we have several hundred years of
我们有几百年的历史
overwhelming evidence to support that
压倒性的证据支持这一点
but every country
但每个国家
practice that one all turn out to be
实践证明一切都是
extraordinarily prosperous
异常繁荣
now we also have a several hundred years
现在我们还有几百年
of history
历史的
a free market is a practice in the
自由市场是一种实践
financial market they're full of
他们充满了金融市场
disasters
灾难
up and down and tree movement
上下和树木运动
it doesn't really work nearly as well
它实际上并没有那么好用
when it comes to financial assets
当涉及到金融资产时
why is it
这是为什么
well the financial asset at the core in
以及以金融资产为核心的
essence
本质
is a discounted mechanism
是一种折扣机制
to predict the future
预测未来
it's the discounted estimated
这是估计的折扣
cash earnings into the infinity
现金收益无穷大
and of course we all know a we cannot
当然我们都知道我们不能
predict infinity would be we can't even
预测无穷大我们甚至不能
predict
预测
immediately beyond what we can see which
立即超出我们所能看到的范围
is usually very short
通常很短
and so there's a necessary element of a
所以有一个必要的元素
speculation and guessing estimation
推测和猜测估计
into the valuations of financial asset
金融资产的估值
when that is exaggerated there is an
当这被夸大时，就会有一个
element in stock market and the
股票市场的要素和
financial market in general the element
一般金融市场要素
of a gambling
一场赌博的
element of a guessing element of a
猜测 a 的元素
speculation
猜测
and as we all know in pure casinos and
众所周知，在纯粹的赌场中
pure gambling
纯粹赌博
there is a huge advantage stock against
有一个巨大的优势股票
players
玩家
and really to the benefit of a casino
确实有利于赌场
owners who define their news
定义新闻的所有者
this is why gambling is such a
这就是为什么赌博如此
profitable
有利可图的
business
商业
and yet that has never really
然而这从来没有真正
persuaded the people away from gambling
劝说人们远离赌博
there is certain element
有一定的元素
uh that really fit human nation and love
呃，真的很适合人类民族和爱情
gamble
赌博
even if everybody knows the oz is
即使每个人都知道盎司是
stacked against
堆积在
that has never protected
从未被保护过的
prevented gambling from a very big
防止赌博规模很大
business especially when it's allowed
业务，尤其是在允许的情况下
ascension by the government
政府的提升
such as a practice in nevada or macau in
例如内华达州或澳门的做法
certain different geographies around the
周围某些不同的地理区域
world
世界
and so there is some aspect of that one
所以这个问题有某个方面
in the financial market as well and this
在金融市场也是如此
is the reason why
这就是为什么
that
那个
it does not work
它不起作用
perfectly well as recently illustrated
正如最近所展示的那样
by the
由
2008-2009
financial crisis which is only in the
金融危机只发生在
stream of a long history of financial
源远流长的金融历史
crisis
危机
but it doesn't really mean
但这并不意味着
that we have a better way of dealing
我们有更好的处理方式
with that
与那个
so it's just as the churchill said about
所以正如丘吉尔所说
democracy is perhaps the worst except
民主也许是最糟糕的，除了
when comparison all the others
当比较所有其他人时
and so is the market
市场也是如此
so it's the free market
所以这是自由市场
when it comes to financial assets
当涉及到金融资产时
it doesn't work very well
效果不太好
attorney doesn't work nearly as well as
律师的工作几乎不那么好
goods and services
商品和服务
but it's still
但它仍然
one of the better ways we have come up
我们想出的更好的方法之一
with
与
in terms of the facilitating flow to
在促进流向方面
finance
金融
which is a white hole for the
这是一个白洞
workings of modern economy
现代经济的运作
so it doesn't so it works
所以它不会，所以它有效
so that really doesn't give us the
所以这确实没有给我们
challenge as a value investor a true
作为一个真正的价值投资者的挑战
value investor
价值投资者
you just have to really reframe
你只需要真正重新构建
yourself from betting too often
自己避免过于频繁地投注
knowing that the financial market
知道金融市场
doesn't really work too well but a lot
效果不是很好，但是很多
of the time it works reasonably well
它工作得相当好
and so you want to really wait for the
所以你想真正等待
extreme situation before you can really
在你真正能够做到的极端情况之前
make a bet
打赌
so that you have a level of margin of
这样你就有了一定的利润水平
safety
安全
and b
和b
that you can actually stand
你实际上可以忍受
against the whole market that do happen
针对整个市场确实发生的情况
that requires an extreme discipline
这需要严格的纪律
of
的
of demanding a large amount of margin of
要求大量保证金
safety
安全
virtually all the successful
几乎所有成功的
value investor practitioners really have
价值投资者从业者确实有
all that
所有这些
element in common they do not bed often
共同点是他们不经常睡觉
and whenever they bet they require a
每当他们下注时，他们都需要
large large amount of marginal safety
大量 大量 边际安全
so that they will be comfortable in case
以便他们在万一发生时感到舒适
the market works against them
市场对他们不利
and so that they are seizing the
以便他们抓住
opportunities that almost no-brainer
几乎不费脑子的机会
and that really is the most difficult
这确实是最困难的
challenges
挑战
most of people really has uh
大多数人确实有呃
do not really have the necessary
确实没有必要
discipline mental discipline to do that
遵守精神纪律来做到这一点
and so you would have saved any
所以你会保存任何
in the bull market everybody practice
牛市大家都练
everybody used to call themselves
每个人都曾经称呼自己
investors
投资者
they buy something they think there is a
他们买一些他们认为有的东西
20 discount to what they think is an
他们认为的 20 折扣
intrinsic value
内在价值
uh
呃
and and
和和
when this goes up and they really trump
当这个上升并且他们真的胜出时
themselves as a successful intelligent
作为一个成功的聪明人
and valid in the investor but then when
并且对投资者有效，但是当
the market would be against them which
市场将会反对他们
is very easy
很容易
twenty percent of discount is almost
百分之二十的折扣差不多了
within the error margin and they're
在误差范围内，他们是
right
对
if the market began to and you would
如果市场开始，你会
have said it would be the first one
已经说过这将是第一个
respect the market runs
尊重市场运行
that's typically the case
通常是这样的
and so when you see a situation like
所以当你看到类似的情况时
that that is usually a sign that's not
这通常是一个迹象，但不是
true
真实
that is as it's properly practiced so as
这就是正确练习的结果
a young student a young analyst or
年轻学生 年轻分析师 或
somebody who's interested in finance
对金融感兴趣的人
i would strongly encourage you the best
我会强烈鼓励你做到最好
way to do that is to study
做到这一点的方法就是学习
successful practices in real life and
现实生活中的成功实践
examples or history
例子或历史
studied very well all the examples of
很好地研究了所有的例子
great
太棒了
value investing decisions
价值投资决策
i was talking to eisner on the way from
我在去的路上和艾斯纳说话
the airport to pick me up so we talked
机场接我所以我们聊了聊
about
关于
his favorite stocking russian oil which
他最喜欢的俄罗斯石油
reminds me one of those
让我想起其中之一
green examples of valiant investing back
勇敢投资的绿色范例
in the early 90s
90年代初
as some of you might know in the early
你们中的一些人可能在早期就知道
90s a russian but through a shock
90年代的俄罗斯人却经历了震惊
therapy
治疗
and went into
并进入
a free market almost overnight in short
简而言之，自由市场几乎在一夜之间就形成了
period of time they privatized some of
有一段时间他们将一些私有化
the most surprised
最惊讶的
finance state assets including local oil
为包括地方石油在内的国有资产提供融资
gas problems to talk about and
气体问题要谈论和
it was so short
太短了
that most people don't really understand
大多数人并不真正理解
what it's all about
这是怎么回事
a lot of the people who work in the
很多在工作中工作的人
companies and also other citizens will
公司和其他公民将
give a certificate
颁发证书
about their that can really convert it
关于他们真正可以改变它的
to stock ownership but most people
但大多数人都持股
really don't know what it is so anybody
真的不知道这是什么所以有人
will come along offer them a real cash
会来给他们真正的现金
which they recognize they were just
他们认识到他们只是
afraid to give it away
害怕把它放弃
so as a result of the certificate
所以作为证书的结果
at one point it was retreating as an
在某一时刻，它作为一种
extraordinarily low prices
价格极低
how low is the prices
价格有多低
forget about the earnings
忘记收入
just to sort of the asset on the balance
只是为了对余额上的资产进行排序
sheet
片材
at the time the oil prices i think in
我认为当时的油价
the
的
four or five year average around twenty
四五年平均二十左右
dollars
美元
and the reserve represented by the
和储备金代表
balance sheet partial basis value the
资产负债表部分基值
per value of the oil per barrel of the
每桶石油的价值
proven reserve at a really low prices as
探明储量以非常低的价格
do you remember what was the price
你还记得价格是多少吗
anybody remember
有人记得吗
it was 20 dollars
是 20 美元
per barrel traded on the open market
每桶在公开市场上交易
anybody can imagine how low they built
任何人都可以想象他们的建筑有多低
one cents
一分钱
on the dollar sometimes
有时对美元
half says on the dollar in other words
换句话说，一半是针对美元的
about 10 cents to 20 cents per proven
每个已证实的约 10 美分到 20 美分
barrier of oil on the balance sheet
资产负债表上的石油屏障
and that's not even counting the
这还不包括
earnings
收益
from the company this is how low it went
从公司来看，这就是它的低点
it was ridiculous
这太荒谬了
now i thought at that point that's some
现在我想那是一些
kind of a margin of safety
某种安全边际
even consider
甚至考虑
uh the political situation in russia and
呃俄罗斯的政治局势和
it ultimately traded up you know for the
它最终换成了你知道的
longest period of time it was a 20 30
最长的一段时间是20 30
cents 50 cents
美分 50 美分
briefly traded to three dollars
短暂交易至三美元
and then a few years later the asian
然后几年后亚洲
financial crisis
金融危机
occurred and russia devalued the
发生了，俄罗斯贬值了
currencies all of a sudden that two
突然间两种货币
dollar oil no longer looks very
美元石油看起来不再那么重要
protected because the currents are
受到保护，因为电流是
literally one point it went down ninety
实际上下降了九十分之一
percent i mean nine zero
百分比我的意思是九个零
but if you really bought it in the ten
但如果你真的在十天内买了它
cents which is a half cents half percent
分，即半分半
of the value
的价值
less than you know now the 10 the value
小于你现在知道的 10 的值
turns it down 90 you still came out
把它调低90你还是出来了
quite all right
很好
in fact you still probably made it 10
事实上你仍然可能达到 10
times your money
倍你的钱
that's how an extreme situation can
这就是极端情况下的情况
become that will be a good example to
成为一个很好的例子
study
学习
so you can really withstand a situation
这样你就能真正承受住某种情况
external shock that really shocked that
外部冲击确实令人震惊
one of the measure of value in this case
在这种情况下的价值衡量标准之一
currency by 90 you still came up on top
货币到 90 你仍然名列前茅
that is how extreme it is that concept
这就是这个概念有多极端
will mark your safety when you do
当您这样做时会标记您的安全
practice
练习
take another example a few years
再举一个几年后的例子
afterwards
之后
back in 97 98
97年回来 98年
the oil
油
open market worldwide it traded below
全球开放市场，其交易价格如下
ten dollars
十美元
for a period of the several months
持续数月的时间
at the time
当时
the five-year averages are probably
五年平均数可能是
twenty years
二十年
as i said before
正如我之前所说
but
但是
also the majority actually if not all of
事实上，即使不是全部，也是大多数
the productions on the west is above ten
西部的产量在十以上
dollars cost
美元成本
exxon mobil you know
埃克森美孚你知道吗
you name it everything outside
你把外面的一切都命名为
uh saudi arabia couple
呃沙特阿拉伯夫妇
gulf state countries a little part of
海湾国家的一小部分
russia part of those a small
俄罗斯，其中一小部分
portion it's not that small but it's
部分不是那么小，但它是
still a fraction of the overall
仍占总体的一小部分
production
生产
everybody's become
每个人都变成了
unprofitable at ten dollars per hour
每小时十美元无利可图
and at the time we have not really
当时我们还没有真正
figured out uh
想通了呃
how to replace voting
如何替代投票
and so
等等
there were plenty plenty companies at
有很多公司
the
的
uh time not losing money even at
呃时间即使在
attendance
出席率
and who's really making a great and who
谁真正取得了伟大的成就，谁
has a huge amount of on the balance
有大量余额
sheet
片材
and you can calculate
你可以计算
as to what it is about you per
关于你的什么
share and so there are really examples
分享，所以确实有例子
of examples of the examples so in every
例子的例子所以在每个
period of time as i was in business this
我做生意的那段时间
is from the mid 90s
是从90年代中期开始
90s 94
90年代94
95 so it's nearly 20 years
95 已经快20年了
i've never really uh
我从来没有真正呃
go through a period of time that i
经历一段时间我
couldn't really find something just
实在找不到东西
enticing and interesting
诱人又有趣
so if you especially operate a smaller
所以如果你特别经营一个较小的
pool of the money at any time
随时有资金池
because you're really kind of choosing
因为你真的在选择
from 100 000
100 000起
different
不同的
securities mostly stocks all over the
证券主要是各地的股票
world
世界
there are always opportunities like that
总是有这样的机会
that give you plenty of margin of safety
给你足够的安全边际
but of course the most interesting thing
但当然最有趣的是
you want to do
你想做
is not only to talk about the asset
不仅仅是谈论资产
you're talking about enduring burning
你说的是持久燃烧
generating franchise a compounding
产生特许经营权和复利
machine in other words
换句话说，机器
if you can combine the cheap prices on
如果你能结合便宜的价格
the asset there's also the quality of
资产还有质量
the asset the ability to consistently
资产始终如一的能力
generate cash
产生现金
earnings on a compound and growing basis
复合增长的收益
that is the holy grail that you can
这就是你可以做到的圣杯
really hold for longest period of time
真正保持最长时间
and no matter what
无论如何
the market is really for against you you
市场真的是在反对你
can really basically ignore it
真的基本上可以忽略它
now does a situation like that exist
现在有这样的情况吗
i would argue it does
我认为确实如此
maybe not for the larger amount of
也许不是为了更大的数量
capital the smaller cap amount of the
资本 较小的上限金额
capital if i were a student today
资本如果我今天是一名学生
and it has a few tens of thousands of
它有几万个
dollars i'll be really very happy to
美元我真的很高兴
live in the environment as it is today
生活在今天的环境中
now if i have a larger amount of money
现在如果我有更多的钱
we have multiple challenges all over the
我们在各地都面临着多重挑战
world
世界
which we cannot really go into today but
我们今天不能真正讨论这个问题，但是
if you have a smaller pool of money
如果你的资金较少
there are tremendous opportunities like
有巨大的机会，比如
that in all small pockets
在所有小口袋里
i give you one uh an example that you
我给你举个例子，你
can really do more work to see whether
真的可以做更多的工作看看是否
it's interesting
很有趣
in career
在职业生涯中
there's a
有一个
form of a securities how to prefer
证券形式 如何选择
securities essentially it is a
证券本质上是一种
non-voting comment stock
无投票权评论股票
that
那个
pays slightly more preferred dividend
支付略多的优先股股息
not much
不多
but it cannot vote
但它不能投票
but for
但是为了
interesting reasons
有趣的原因
that they are trading sometimes up to 70
他们的交易有时高达 70
80 discount
80折
to their common equipment
到他们的共同设备
and in that group of securities there
在那组证券中
are several companies that really have
有几家公司真正拥有
enduring franchise
持久的特许经营权
that have been growing
一直在增长的
earnings and revenue on a compounded
收益和收入按复利计算
basis
基础
for over three or four decades
超过三、四十年
because the franchise is nearly as a
因为特许经营权几乎是
fortress with uh
堡垒与呃
purchase life
购买生活
great earning power machines that still
仍然具有巨大盈利能力的机器
have a lot of opportunity of expansion
有很多扩展的机会
and trading at uh
并在呃进行交易
prices that uh is essentially just tiny
价格基本上很小
fraction of what really should be
真正应该的一小部分
worth in an open and a private
开放和私人的价值
transaction if you buy the whole company
如果您购买整个公司的交易
in fact you have really a comparison
事实上你确实有一个比较
of the common stock in a voting common
有投票权的普通股中的普通股
stock equivalent
股票等价物
a situation just like that really exists
类似的情况确实存在
even today
即使在今天
there's absolutely no reason especially
绝对没有特别的理由
some of those companies that i talk
我谈到的一些公司
about it
关于它
the family really controls the voting of
家族真正控制着投票权
the common anyway
无论如何都是常见的
so there is virtually no differences
所以几乎没有区别
between the common the voting common and
普通股之间 投票普通股 和
non-voting time there was virtually no
非投票时间几乎没有
no differences
没有差异
and yet the training was eighty percent
然而训练却是百分之八十
uh disco i'm not talking about twenty
呃迪斯科我说的不是二十岁
percent this time eighty percent discuss
这次百分之八十讨论
trading the twenty cents on the dollar
以美元二十美分进行交易
if you believe that that common language
如果你相信那种共同语言
is like the truth true value
就像真理的真实价值
so the opportunity that my point is
所以我的观点是机会
really existed on all the different ones
确实存在于所有不同的人身上
so if you're starting your career if
所以如果你正在开始你的职业生涯
you're young if i were you starting all
如果我是你开始一切，你还年轻
over again
再来一次
i would have first to study
我首先要学习
all the grading examples in the past
过去所有的评分示例
in which the market went to the extreme
市场走向极端
on a small segment until the security
一小段直到安全
that gives you a tremendous tremendous
这给了你一个巨大的巨大
margin of safety
安全边际
now all sorts of things happen and you
现在发生了各种各样的事情，而你
are still come out okay
仍然出来好吗
even if you lose money you're still in
即使你亏了钱你仍然在
the game
游戏
study that one and then study what is
研究那个，然后研究是什么
available today
今天有空
at any given time there are always
在任何给定的时间总是有
always opportunities like that
总是有这样的机会
it really has something to do with our
这确实与我们有关
fundamental human psychology
基本人类心理学
as long as human remains the same which
只要人类保持不变
i suspected will after billions of years
我怀疑数十亿年后会
that opportunity exists
这个机会是存在的
which is quite an encouraging sign for
这是一个非常令人鼓舞的迹象
young people so if i were you i would
年轻人，所以如果我是你，我会
have been very excited today as i was
今天和我一样非常兴奋
when i was sitting in the audience in
当我坐在观众席上时
your shoe
你的鞋
about
关于
20 years ago
20年前
so good luck for that i'll open for
祝你好运，我会开放的
questions
问题
[Applause]
[鼓掌]
yeah i have a question now
是的，我现在有一个问题
when do we just how do you decide when
我们什么时候做 你如何决定什么时候
you sell this stuff
你卖这个东西
well it's a very interesting question
这是一个非常有趣的问题
now
现在
it depends what's the source of your
这取决于你的来源是什么
value
值
is some of the example that i stated the
是我所说的一些例子
source of the value it really is the is
其真正价值的来源是
the asset value
资产价值
and in that case you really
在那种情况下你真的
want to really re-evaluate your
想要真正重新评估你的
scenarios up
场景向上
side and downside
侧面和缺点
every once in a while because the
每隔一段时间，因为
situation changes for example in your
情况发生变化，例如您的
favorite stock and the russian oil the
最喜欢的股票和俄罗斯石油
local oils
当地的油
and gas problems i sold it two years
和煤气问题我把它卖了两年
after i first bought it
当我第一次买它之后
[Music]
[音乐]
and they just other but at the time
他们只是其他但当时
there's still kind of a treating
还有一种治疗方法
probably 90 percent
大概90%
80 to 90 percent discount but i think
80% 到 90% 的折扣，但我认为
the 80 90 discount is warranted somehow
80 90 的折扣是有道理的
today it is still trading at a huge
今天它的交易价格仍然很高
discount i don't know what it is you're
折扣我不知道你是什么
probably more updated than i do
可能比我更新得更多
but relative to all the other countries
但相对于所有其他国家
that i would feel less comfortable
我会感觉不太舒服
with that discount i mean more
有了这个折扣，我意味着更多
and it just happened to be given a 99
而它恰好得到了 99 分
just come 99.9
刚来99.9
percent discount that was that was a
百分比折扣 那是
fluke
侥幸
now if you're really talking about
现在如果你真的在谈论
earnings
收益
i tend to be less uh in a hurry
我不太着急
because if you really bet it right
因为如果你真的赌对了
the earning will continue to grow
收入将持续增长
and every time you sell stock you
每次你出售股票时
basically take out
基本上拿出来
essentially a 30 to 40 percent
基本上是 30% 到 40%
of of interest-free borrow
无息借款
by not really selling the stock you
不真正出售你的股票
avoided paying the capital gain taxes
避免缴纳资本利得税
uh the state of federal together is
呃联邦州一起是
somewhere in 20 30 to 40 i think it's
我认为在 20 30 到 40 之间
going up
上升
as long as you're in that in a sense
只要你在某种意义上处于其中
you're borrowing from the government on
你从政府借钱
the interest-free and risk-free basis
无息和无风险的基础
and if the asset
如果资产
underlying
底层的
asset continue to grow on a compounded
资产继续以复利增长
basis
基础
i would say
我想说
that is reason to be less in hurry to
这就是不那么着急的原因
sell
卖
if it reflects in the uh fair value i
如果它反映在呃公允价值中我
would
会
uh keep it but if they really go through
嗯，留着吧，但如果他们真的经历了
the extreme overvalue situations and the
极端高估的情况和
business environment changes
营商环境变化
of course you change your course of
当然你改变你的路线
action and that's a good thing about uh
行动，这是一件好事
investing everything related
投资一切相关的东西
and affected investment
以及受影响的投资
all the circumstances changes all the
所有的情况都改变了
time that's why the game is so fun
时间，这就是游戏如此有趣的原因
yeah hi
是啊嗨
i was wondering what is the margin of
我想知道利润是多少
safety that you look for before you
您所寻求的安全
decided to buy
决定购买
yeah again that has something to do with
是的，这又与
the quality of the asset if you're
资产的质量，如果您是
buying
购买
if the quality of the asset is very high
如果资产质量非常高
your demand on asset basis is a low
您对资产的需求较低
because you are
因为你是
uh you are demanding that a margin of
呃，你要求的余量是
safety on the upside in terms of the
安全性在上行方面
earning generating power
赚取发电量
whatever it is you have to have an
不管是什么，你必须有一个
insight as to what this asset can
了解该资产可以做什么
generate for you
为你生成
and somehow it is somewhat of a
不知怎的，这有点像
difference inside a unique insight
独特见解中的差异
whether you know the business
你是否了解这个行业
particularly better than anybody else's
特别是比任何人都好
if you really buy into the future
如果你真的相信未来
earnings
收益
or the asset for whatever reason you can
或出于任何原因的资产
withstand the balance sheet better
更好地承受资产负债表
than the other people you have to have a
比其他人你必须有一个
better insight as to what is the
更好地了解什么是
appropriate value and therefore it may
适当的值，因此可以
not really appear to other people as
并不真正在其他人看来
enlarged enough of a margin in your mind
在你的脑海中扩大足够的余量
you have a very very large margin safety
你有非常非常大的安全边际
in my own case i just think that the
就我自己而言，我只是认为
larger you can get it the better
越大越好
you want to have a very very large
你想要一个非常非常大的
safety right right so how about assuming
安全是对的，那么假设怎么样
that you have no insights whatsoever as
你没有任何见解
to what the
到什么
future earnings power is and you just
未来的盈利能力是，而你只是
assume that it's a no growth business
假设这是一项没有增长的业务
what would you pay for that business
你愿意为这项业务支付什么费用
well in the case of the russians since i
就俄罗斯人而言，因为我
know very little about russian i have
我对俄语知之甚少
every reason to be suspect suspicious
一切值得怀疑的理由
so that goes to 99
这样就到了 99
and i get extremely uncomfortable when
当我感到非常不舒服时
it goes to eighty percent for example
例如，它会达到百分之八十
and in the end and actually that ninety
最后，实际上那九十
percent evaporated because of the
蒸发百分比是因为
currency changes although they came back
尽管他们回来了，但货币发生了变化
uh so each situation is different but in
呃，所以每种情况都不同，但在
in in the environment i understand the
在我理解的环境中
external forces i understand the
外部力量我理解
management i understand the general
管理我了解一般情况
business practice in that particular
该特定业务实践
culture you would probably you know 70
您可能了解的文化 70
80 is actually pretty good
80其实也不错
it's all a situation specific
这都是具体情况
okay i just have to say that that's a
好吧，我只想说那是
pretty high hurdle rate
相当高的门槛率
well that's why you don't have to my
好吧，这就是为什么你不必我的
whole point is you don't have to swing a
重点是你不必摇摆
lot
很多
one of the key of a success for
成功的关键之一
being a long-term successful investor is
成为一名长期成功的投资者
you have to endure a long period of time
你必须忍受很长一段时间
in which you do nothing
你什么都不做
you don't have to do a lot in order to
你不必做很多事情
be fabulously rich and prosperous
变得异常富有和繁荣
that's the good thing about to this game
这就是这个游戏的好处
you study all the time but you don't
你一直在学习，但你却没有
have to do anything
必须做任何事
and every time you do when you don't
每次当你不这样做时
have enough market of safety you can
有足够的安全市场你可以
come out to really
真正出来
lose
失去
and that's the really
这才是真正的
much worse thing than really
比实际情况更糟糕的事情
than doing nothing but every time you do
胜过什么都不做，但每次你做的时候
do something
做某事
if you have large enough of a margin of
如果你有足够大的余量
safety
安全
your upside has also become huge and
你的优势也变得巨大
then there are many many examples and i
然后还有很多很多例子，我
wouldn't have time to go into it
没有时间深入探讨
and in which when you turn it when you
当你转动它时
turn out to be right
事实证明是对的
the upside is just enormous you could
好处是巨大的
really surprise your wildest dreams
真正让你最疯狂的梦想感到惊讶
and you want to wait for those fat
而你想等待那些胖子
pitches most of the time okay and then
大部分时间都可以，然后
lastly how much cash are you holding now
最后你现在持有多少现金
that is different from time to time it
这是不时不同的
depends on the
取决于
hi i'm opportunity from berkeley um i'm
嗨，我是来自伯克利的机会，嗯，我是
curious to share your opinion on what
很想分享您对什么的看法
you think are the domestic industry
你以为是国内产业
segments you think are most overvalued
您认为最被高估的细分市场
and undervalued today
今天被低估
well i i
好吧，我我
you know
你知道
there is as i said that
正如我所说
to be a successful investor you don't
成为一名成功的投资者，你做不到
really have to know everything
真的必须知道一切
you don't have to be a
你不必是
who claims he knows everything every
谁声称他知道一切
stock
库存
uh
呃
in fact that if you truly know something
事实上，如果你真正了解某件事
that
那个
you fall into a small circle
你陷入了一个小圈子
uh buffett would like to the manga would
呃巴菲特想要漫画
like to call a circle of confidence you
喜欢叫一圈信任你
want to find in your circle that circle
想在你的圈子里找到那个圈子
tends to be small
往往很小
so every time you hear people talking
所以每次你听到人们说话
about oh gee i think that industry is
关于哦，天哪，我认为这个行业是
over this industry
超过这个行业
is is undervalued
is 被低估
i
我
that is not intellectually honest to me
这对我来说在理智上并不诚实
at least
至少
investing the last thing you want is to
投资你最不想做的事就是
have that error of error
有那个错误的错误
you know arrogance might be a too strong
你知道傲慢可能太强烈了
word but
词但是
i think the more honest you are
我觉得你越诚实
intellectually the more prosperous you
智力上你越繁荣
tend to me
倾向于我
i have never failed any intellectually
我在智力上从来没有失败过
inherited people who can successfully
能够成功继承的人
practice the game of the investment
练习投资游戏
first of all thank you for coming
首先感谢您的到来
you talk about finding you know great
你谈到发现你很了解
financial dislocations to try and find
尝试寻找财务混乱
these tremendous upside situations
这些巨大的上行形势
would you maybe expound on your
你可以解释一下你的
research like how do you find these
研究一下你如何找到这些
these great dislocations where things
这些巨大的混乱
are trading in ten percent of what they
他们的交易额只有百分之十
were
是
well
嗯
i i find as i liked it in my own career
我发现我在自己的职业生涯中喜欢它
of all the ideas that i find they really
在我发现的所有想法中，它们确实
tend to come from
往往来自
all sources
所有来源
i don't have a particular rule where
我没有特定的规则
they come from
他们来自
if you
如果你
have a curious mind if you study all the
如果你研究所有的东西，就会有一颗好奇的心
time you maintain a good network of
是时候保持良好的人际网络了
relationships with other smart
与其他聪明人的关系
intelligent investors that have a way of
聪明的投资者有办法
really looking at what they do
真正关注他们所做的事情
you tend to find a lot of us first of
你往往首先会发现我们很多人
all interesting ideas
所有有趣的想法
and in today's age
在当今时代
because
因为
this regular requirement was disclosure
这一常规要求是披露
i wouldn't be surprised you can really
我不会感到惊讶你真的可以
find a lot of great ideas
发现很多好主意
uh just out of reading publicly
呃刚刚不再公开阅读
available information it is judging what
它正在判断可用的信息
is a good opportunity
是一个好机会
that is really difficult
这真的很难
what's the process like have you uh
你的过程是怎样的呃
finally developed a conviction an idea
最终形成了一个信念和一个想法
is that kind of like an aha moment or do
是不是有点像顿悟时刻或者做的
you describe how you come to that
你描述一下你是如何做到这一点的
conviction level well one of my favorite
信念水平是我最喜欢的之一
way to describe the uh
描述呃的方式
conviction of idea is
想法的信念是
that if you can find the most
如果你能找到最多
intelligent person who would oppose your
聪明的人会反对你
idea
想法
and you're able to argue more
你可以更多地争论
successfully than he does against your
比他对抗你更成功
idea that is when you can develop or
当你可以发展或
entitle to some views
有权发表一些意见
and even then you want to really confine
即使这样你也想真正限制
yourself to a small segment
自己到一小部分
of things that you think you're right
你认为自己正确的事情
of course as you
当然像你一样
gain more experiences your circle tends
获得更多你的圈子里的经验
to expand
扩大
but only small and gradually
但只是小规模的、逐渐的
over time
随着时间的推移
so i think of being intellectually
所以我想在智力上
honest is a huge requirement for being a
诚实是成为一个人的巨大要求
successful analyst and a successful
成功的分析师和成功的分析师
investor
投资者
yes sir thank you for coming today i uh
是的，先生，谢谢你今天来我呃
wanted to ask you a question about
想问你一个问题
portfolio construction and
投资组合构建和
uh just hear your comments on
呃，只是听听你的评论
diversification in the last session
上届会议的多元化
there was a lot of discussion about
有很多讨论
diversification and the importance of it
多元化及其重要性
um my sense is that you're more of a
嗯，我的感觉是你更像是
concentrated investor some other
集中投资者 其他
investors are like that where where does
投资者都这样 哪里哪里
that what kind of role does
那是什么样的角色
diversification play or how do you think
多元化玩法还是你觉得如何
of it in building a portfolio
在建立投资组合时
well you always have to have some kind
好吧，你总是必须有某种
of a
的一个
diversification
多元化
uh
呃
because a you could be wrong and b even
因为 a 你可能是错的 b 甚至
if you're right
如果你是对的
you're betting on statistics
你押注于统计数据
in other words the future is essentially
换句话说，未来本质上是
a distribution of all probabilities
所有概率的分布
so
所以
let's see you have a 90
让我们看看你有 90 分
conviction
信念
and you're right
你是对的
that event is 90 but then 10 chances
该事件是 90 但随后有 10 次机会
happen
发生
and so you don't want to that 10
所以你不想那 10
to get you out of the game
让你退出游戏
so you do need to diversification
所以你确实需要多元化
on the other hand
另一方面
that
那个
recognizing
认出
uh
呃
is extremely rare to find no-brainer
非常罕见，无需动脑筋就能找到
great opportunities extremely rare
绝佳机会极为难得
in fact you have to wait for a long time
事实上你要等很长时间
for the fat fish to come to you
让肥鱼来找你
so when that happens
所以当这种情况发生时
you certainly do not want to diversify
你当然不想多元化
away the opportunity that you have been
失去你曾经拥有的机会
waiting patiently for a long time to
耐心等待很长时间
discover for some really inferior other
发现一些真正劣等的人
opportunities
机会
the investment is essentially is the
投资本质上是
opportunity cost
机会成本
so one other
所以另一个
alternative have to really just by
替代方案必须真的只是通过
itself by comparing it with the one you
通过将其与您自己进行比较
already have
已经有
and so when you make that comparison you
所以当你进行比较时你
tend not to really diversify too much
往往不会真正过度多元化
you want to find it feel
你想要找到它的感觉
very very good ones that have a very
非常非常好的，有一个非常
high
高
uh conviction that might arise
呃，可能会出现的信念
and so yes you you do a little bit both
所以是的，你两者都做了一点
so in that example and you're kind of
所以在那个例子中你是这样的
hitting precisely what i'm getting at
准确击中我的意思
in a very high conviction idea
以非常高的信念
what do you feel the the limits are in
你觉得极限在哪里
terms of you know how much you could be
你知道你能成为多少
invested and what you know what
投资和你知道什么
considerations do you have
你有什么考虑
well i would say as i said that all
好吧，我想说的是，正如我所说的那样
decisions ought to be able to through
决策应该能够通过
the concept of the opportunity cost is
机会成本的概念是
what else can i do with the cash i have
我还能用我拥有的现金做什么
and cash by the way
顺便说一句还有现金
is a really a fundamentally important
确实是一个非常重要的
asset and if i don't really find
资产，如果我没有真正找到
anything else or if i find a bunch of
还有什么或者如果我找到一堆
other opportunity fear into cash
其他机会恐惧变成现金
then i would have given him cash
那我就给他现金
and so
等等
i i would say that
我我会这么说
that i
那我
i it never bothers me you know with a
我从来不打扰我你知道
large amount of cash i can't find a
大量现金我找不到
great opportunities
巨大的机会
at the same time when i find say one
同时当我发现说一个
good ideas i'll let it
好主意我会放手的
get
得到
a little bigger percentage of the
稍微大一点的比例
of the
的
of the portfolio and then everything
投资组合，然后是一切
else will compare with what i already
否则将与我已经的进行比较
have which is cash
有现金
and sometimes holding cash can be the
有时持有现金可能是
result of a bottom-up research
自下而上研究的结果
i always believe that's the case
我始终相信情况就是如此
okay well thank you very much
好的，非常感谢
[Applause]
[鼓掌]